Guide to the Professor Loyd S. Swenson Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Professor Loyd S. Swenson Papers
1977-1987
1988-002
Swenson, Loyd S.
26.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The processed portion of these papers includes 12 linear feet described in five series. They comprise the editorial files for 100 Years of Science and Technology in Texas, published by Rice University Press in 1986. Professor Swenson, of the University of Houston, and Reverend Leo Klosterman, of the University of St. Thomas, co-edited the work, which was sponsored by Sigma Xi, a scientific research society. The materials date from 1977 to 1987.
Biographical Information:
Loyd S. Swenson, Jr., was one of the editors for 100 Years of Science and Technology in Texas, published by Rice University Press in 1986. A professor of history at the University of Houston, he is a member of Sigma Xi, which sponsored the volume tracing scientific developments in Texas during the hundred year history of Sigma Xi.
The Southeast Texas Sigma Xi Council (SETSXC) was established in 1984 in an effort to help promote and coordinate activities surrounding the centennial of Sigma Xi, founded in 1886. Nine chapters in southeastern Texas joined together to better promote the centennial and other related activities. The publication of 100 Years of Science and Technology in Texas, was one of the major activities undertaken by SETSXC during the centennial year. Other activities sponsored by SETSXC included speakers and open houses at different universities and companies.
The Sigma Xi Centennial was promoted in conjunction with sesquicentennial activities for Texas independence, as well as the founding of the city of Houston.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Society of the Sigma Xi
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence; Galley proofs; Minutes; Notes; Page proofs; Typescripts
Geographic Name:
Texas -- History -- 1951-
Topical Term:
Science -- Texas -- History; Technology -- Texas -- History
Acquisition Information:
Donated by Professor Loyd S. Swenson, Jr. 6 boxes of unprocessed archival materials were donated on April 30, 2015. 2 additional boxes of unprocessed archival materials were donated on June 11, 2015. 6 additional boxes of unprocessed archival materials were donated on December 14, 2015.
Separated Materials:
Materials Removed from the Collection:
Five catalogs from various university presses from 1985.
All but two copies of a set of page proofs listing the contributors to the work.
Copies of the Robert A. Welch Foundation publications (research bulletins and annual reports), which are located in the University of Houston Pharmacy Library.
5 boxes of books related to Einstein that arrived in the April 30, 2015 addition.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Scope and Contents
The processed portion of these papers includes 12 linear feet described in five series. They comprise the editorial files for 100 Years of Science and Technology in Texas, published by Rice University Press in 1986. Professor Swenson, of the University of Houston, and Reverend Leo Klosterman, of the University of St. Thomas, co-edited the work, which was sponsored by Sigma Xi, a scientific research society. The materials date from 1977 to 1987.
Included are correspondence with publishers, editors, and authors of the chapters in the books. There are also various drafts of the chapters, page proofs, critiques of the chapters by Swenson, Klosterman, and other contributors, galley proofs, notes, chronologies, outlines, and dust jackets. All chapters and proofs have been arranged according to the arrangement of the published work.
There is also a considerable amount of correspondence and materials related to the Southeast Texas Sigma Xi Council, which sponsored the production of the volume. The minutes of the society, which have been left with the correspondence to which they were attached, provide insight into the organizational and financial difficulties encountered in producing the commemorative volume. Additional materials include items related to the Texas Sesquicentennial and the Robert A. Welch Foundation. Among the Welch Foundation materials were annual reports and research bulletins, published between 1977 and 1984, which have been removed from the collection; copies are available in the University of Houston Pharmacy Library.
The collection has been arranged in six series: Correspondence, Drafts, Proofs, Miscellaneous, Sesquicentennial Materials, and Unprocessed Materials (2015 additions).
Detailed List of Contents
- Correspondence, 1984-1987
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes correspondence with contributors as well as correspondence with Sigma Xi members during the period covered by the collection. There is also minimal correspondence with the editors and publishers. There are eighteen folders in this series, with the bulk dating from 1985 to 1986. All correspondence has been arranged chronologically, and attached materials have been kept with their correspondence. Materials sent to Sigma Xi members have a considerable amount of information relating to the status of 100 Years of Science and Technology in Texas.
  - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 2-9)
  - 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11-17)
  - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Drafts, 1985-1986
  This series includes multiple drafts of the various chapters in the book, with the editors’ marks. These chapters have been arranged so that different versions of the same chapter are found together, with the overall arrangement following that of the finished book. This is the largest series in the collection, consisting of 110 folders of materials dating primarily from 1986. The materials have been arranged from earliest draft to latest, where differences could be ascertained. Following the chapter drafts are drafts of indexes, chronologies, and general notes made by the editors. This also includes chronologies, indexes, and other book related material. One draft of the book has a rich set of surveys on the history of Sigma Xi chapters in Texas. These materials precede the drafts of the section.
  - History of Sigma Xi Survey, A-L, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - History of Sigma Xi Survey, M-R, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - History of Sigma Xi Survey, S, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - History of Sigma Xi Survey, T, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - History of Sigma Xi Survey, U-Z, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - History of Sigma Xi Notes, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - History of Sigma Xi Rough Draft, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - History of Sigma Xi, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - History of Sigma Xi I Texas, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Introduction, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Introduction, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Science and Technology in Texas Before World War II, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Science and Technology in Texas Before World War II, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 13-17)
  - Geology in Texas, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Geology in Texas, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
  - Oceanography and Meteorology, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Oceanography, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oceanography in Texas, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 7-11)
  - Chronological History of Meteorology, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Meteorology, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
  - Astronomy in Texas, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Astronomy in Texas, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Space Science and Technology, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 4-6)
  - Mathematics, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 7-9)
  - History of Physics in Texas, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10-12)
  - History of Physics in Texas, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 13-15)
  - Chemistry and Chemical Technology, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Chemistry, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Chemistry and Chemical Technology, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chemistry, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Chemistry and Chemical Technology, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Petroleum Technology, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 6-11)
  - Significant Energy Technology Developments, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Significant Energy Technology Developments, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 13-17)
  - Civil and Mechanical Engineering, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - History of Computing in Texas, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Ecology, Environmental Biology and Natural History, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Ecology, Environmental Biology and Natural History, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
  - Applied Biology: Agriculture, Animal Husbandry, Forestry, and Veterinary Medicine, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9-12)
  - Genetics and Molecular Biology, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 13-14)
  - Genetics, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Health Sciences, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Archaeology and Anthropology, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 5-7)
  - Psychology in Texas before World War II, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 8-11)
  - Psychology in Texas, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 12-13)
  - Psychiatry, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Psychiatry, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 15-19)
  - Scientific Foundations, Societies, and Museums, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Scientific Foundations, Societies, and Museums, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Chapter Summaries, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Chronologies - Chapter, 1985-1986 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Chronologies - Overviews, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Indexes by Chapter - Introduction to Chapter 3, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Indexes by Chapter - Chapter 4 to Chapter 9, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Indexes by Chapter - Chapter 10 to Chapter 20, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Name Indexes by Chapter - Introduction to Chapter 6, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Name Indexes by Chapter - Chapter 7 to Chapter 20, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Notes, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- Proofs, 1986
  This series includes proofs of the individual chapters in the books, with editing marks. The chapter proofs have been arranged to follow the organization of the finished book. There are also two complete sets of galley proofs of the book, as well as an incomplete set of page proofs. There are thirty-five folders of material in the series, all dating from 1986.
  - Contents, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Introduction, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Science and Technology in Texas before World War II, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Science and Technology in Texas from World War II to the Present, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Oceanography, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Meteorology, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Astronomy, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - NASA and the Space Sciences, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Mathematics, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Physics, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Chemistry, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Petroleum and Petrochemical Technology, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Other Energy Technologies, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Civil and Mechanical Engineering, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Computing, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Ecology, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Applied Biology, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Genetics, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Health Sciences, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Archaeology and Anthropology, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Psychology, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Psychiatry, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Scientific Foundations, Societies, and Museums, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Appendix A, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Appendix B, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Tables, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - Complete Set - Corrections, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Complete Set, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 2-3)
  - Miscellaneous Proofs, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 1-5)
- Miscellaneous, 1977-1986
  This series includes any material related to the book that does not fall into the three previous series. There are nineteen folders of material dating from 1985 to 1986. Among the items are photographs, publicity material, publishers’ information, notes, lists of possible buyers, and dust jackets. There are also some Sigma Xi materials.
  - Copyright Information, 1977-1979 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Discovery, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Editorial Information, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Negatives, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Notes, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 11-12)
  - Preliminary Discussions, 1984-1986 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Press Material, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Publishing Information, 1985-1986 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Robert A. Welch Foundation, 1977-1986 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Sales, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Sigma Xi, 1984-1986 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Sigma Xi Centennial, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Texas Colleges and Universities, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Clippings, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dust Jackets, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Editorial Information, 1985-1986 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Journal Listings, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Sesquicentennial Material, 1982-1986
  This series includes local press publications from 1986 documenting the history of Texas. There are also several issues of the National Dispatch, which was the official Texas Sesquicentennial publication. The twelve folders in the series have been arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Houston City, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Magazine of the Houston Post, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - National Dispatch, 1982 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - National Dispatch, 1983 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - National Dispatch, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - National Dispatch, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Spirit of Texas, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Texas Humanist, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Texas Monthly, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - This Weekend, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Times of Texas, 1986 (Box 12, Folder 16)
- Unprocessed additions
  14 linear feet of additional materials were added to this collection in 2015. Accession #2015-029: 6 boxes of materials donated by Professor Svenson on April 30, 2015. Accession #2015-030: 2 additional boxes of unprocessed archival materials were donated on June 11, 2015. Accession #2015-031: 6 additional boxes of unprocessed archival materials were donated on December 14, 2015.